#### Contact

860-944-3247 (Mobile) jrparkny@aol.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ johnparkerrnms (LinkedIn)

Top Skills
CPI Instructor
Team Building
Recruitment/Retention

# John Parker MS, RN

Interim Behavioral Health Nurse Manager at Kirby Bates Associates Hartford, Connecticut Area

# Summary

My history is one of fixing things. I quickly find the root cause of problems and make changes to solve them. I have spent 40 years refining my clinical and administrative leadership abilities.

I have taken a start up hospital through their first Joint Commission Survey successfully. I took a hospital that was floundering from lack of minimal staff, and saw them through The Joint Commission first survey with no citations for nursing.

Quality and profit are not mutually exclusive. Staff satisfaction facilitates patient satisfaction. I have taken patient satisfaction from 53% to 96% in as short as 8 months. Recruiting and retention are key to creating a healthy care team.

My management style is very much hands on. I am on the floors, teaching, discussing, solving problems and this lends itself to nursing staff feeling supported. Good management is the best reason to eliminate feelings of need for collective bargaining but I can and have worked well in union environments keeping in mind that patient care is a mutual goal.

I believe that care cannot be provided without safety of patients and staff. From the cornerstone of a feeling of safety, quality and patient satisfaction is attainable.

I am now doing Behavioral Health consulting.

John R. Parker

Specialties: Leadership & Motivation

Psychiatric Nursing Skills

Advanced Behavioral Health Assessment Skills

Therapeutic Communication

**CPI Trainer** 

**Evidenced Based Training and Clinical Treatment** 

Public speaking

Community Partnerships
Efficient Resource Allocation
Reduction in Cost per Patient Day
Strength Based Treatment
Recovery Focus
Resiliency Centered Treatment
Positive Clinical Outcomes
RN licenses in NH, MA, CT, NY, PA, MD, FL, TX, CA, OR, WA, WY, NC, AL, and SC.

# Experience

Kirby Bates Associates
Interim Behavioral Health Nurse Manager
May 2020 - Present (3 months)
Baltimore, Maryland, United States

Consulting and Managing two Psych Units for the University of Maryland Medical Center in Midtown Baltimore.

HealthTrust Workforce Solutions 5 months

Interim CNO
January 2020 - March 2020 (3 months)
Westborough Behavioral Health Hospital/Detroit Medical Center

Interim Behavioral Health Nursing Director November 2019 - January 2020 (3 months) Assigned to Detroit Medical Center

Expert in TJC/CMS regulations
Elevate staff and patient satisfaction
Safety expert for EOC

Westchester Medical Center, a member of WMCHealth Interim Behavioral Health Nursing Director and Consultant May 2019 - November 2019 (7 months)
Valhalla, NY

HIred as Consultant for 101 bed inpatient behavioral health center and 80 bed behavioral Health sister hospital, then promoted to Interim Behavioral Health Nursing Director for Westchester, and continued as Consultant for Mid Hudson Regional Hospital.

Restored Nursing Staffing, Redesigned Nursing Staffing Patterns, Passed CMS and NVA Surveys.

HealthTrust Workforce Solutions
Interim Program Director
November 2018 - March 2019 (5 months)
South Strand Hospital Myrtle Beach, SC

Interim Program Director to work with employee engagement, expansion and admissions throughput.

Passed Joint Commission survey and CMS survey as well.

### Healthtrust WS

interim Behavioral Health Nursing Director July 2018 - November 2018 (5 months) North Florida Regional Medical Center

31 bed acute adult unit in an HCA hospital

Rebuilt staffing roster, got to full capacity. Increased staff satisfaction/patient satisfaction.

Cambridge Health Alliance Interim Adolescent Assessment Unit Manager May 2018 - June 2018 (2 months) Interim Manager

Innovative Employee Solutions
Interim Director
September 2017 - May 2018 (9 months)
Southeast Alabama Medical Center

THAXTON BARABE - Defining Healthcare Leadership Interim Behavioral Health Director
May 2017 - June 2017 (2 months)
Multicare Tacoma and Auburn Hospitals, WA

**Program Assessment** 

Coaching/Mentoring Nursing Manager and Asst. Managers on Adolescent/ Adult and Geri Psych Units in 2 Multicare Hospitals

Cottage Hospital Interim Program Director February 2017 - April 2017 (3 months)

Woodsville, NH

Mentoring new staff on Start Up Gero-Psych Unit
Prep for CMS Survey in Critical Access Hospital
Increased census/created throughput mechanism/created competency tool
documentation

The First String Healthcare
Inteirm Nursing Manager
August 2016 - February 2017 (7 months)
Manchester, NH

Horizon Healthcare, Inc.
Interim Behavioral Health Nursing Director
June 2016 - August 2016 (3 months)
Taunton, Mass.

6 week assignment to lend stability to 24 bed Geripsych unit

NHS Solutions, Inc.
Interim Director for Clinical and Outpatient Services
July 2015 - March 2016 (9 months)
New London, Connecticut Area

Director for multiple inpatient and outpatient units including Psych Inpatient, Intensive Outpatient Program, Psych ER, Stroke team, PT, OT, SLP, Acute rehab, palliative care, wound care, cardiac rehab, and Respiratory Therapy. Supervising 150+ FTEs.

HCT Executive Interim Management & Consulting Interim Director for Psychiatric Nursing March 2015 - June 2015 (4 months)
Lander, Wyoming

Interim Director for For-profit Hospital. Stabilized psychiatric inpatient program. Functioned as House Supervisor. Improved environment of safety.

Quincy Medical Center
Patient Care Director Behavioral Health Nursing
April 2014 - January 2015 (10 months)
Quincy, MA

Clinical and administrative oversight of 22 bed Geri-Psych Unit.

Calvert Memorial Hospital

#### Director of Behavioral Health

August 2011 - December 2012 (1 year 5 months)

Prince Frederick, MD

Administrative and Clinical Supervision of Acute Psychiatric Inpatient, 2 PHPs and 2 Psychiatric Emergency Services.

Southern Maryland Hospital Center Director, Psychiatric Services and Partial Day Hospital December 2010 - August 2011 (9 months)

### PSI THE VINES HOSPITAL

**Director of Nursing** 

February 2010 - November 2010 (10 months)

88 Bed For-Profit Private Psychiatric Hospital

Selected Achievements

Redesigned Nursing Plan of Care for 31 Bed SIPP

Passed JCAHO survey after 8 months employment

Redesigned Nursing Plan of Care for 57 bed Acute Adult Psychiatric Inpatient

Brought patient satisfaction rate from 53% to 96%

# Natchaug Hospital

**Nursing Operations** 

January 2008 - December 2009 (2 years)

Regional acute impatient psychiatric hospital

Manage day-to-day nursing operations and staff budgets supporting three units comprised of adults, children, and adolescents. Supervise and train 38 direct / indirect reports. Accountable for patient care management, staff training & development, clinical resource management, infection control, emergency treatments, financial performance, and patient screening. Lead patient evaluations in assessing patient's medical and psychiatric conditions.

#### Selected Achievements

Improved reimbursable admissions by streamlining and enhancing processes to screen and evaluate patients for admission.

Reduced operating expenses by successfully realigning acuity levels with staff resources to deliver optimal patient care across operations.

Tracked and managed the authorization and delivery of emergency treatments and care with focus on generating cost savings while maximizing patient satisfaction.

Hartford Hospital/The Institute of Living Manager Unit Operation
May 2002 - August 2009 (7 years 4 months)

Non-profit 812-bed regional hospital organization.

Managed operations for 90-bed acute inpatient psychiatric unit with oversight for strategic program and development driven via project-based process.

Managed and trained 95 direct / indirect reports. Defined and translated business strategies into solutions that met patient care services needs.

Developed and presented clear rationale for research- based decisions and actions. Oversaw an organizational culture that valued and supported research initiatives as part of providing and/or improving patient care and service outcomes.

#### Selected Achievements

Increased bed utilization from 88% to 96% by balancing staff resources across three psychiatric units to provide cost-effective, priority care that met the healthcare needs of patients.

Improved patient satisfaction scores from 75% to 93% by developing and implementing a program to train and educate psychiatric nurses in proper medical care.

Worked closely with peers and colleagues in devising and executing clearly define workable solutions to ensure consistency and continuity of patient care services across psychiatric operations.

Quinnipiac University
Adjunct Clinical Professor
January 2007 - May 2007 (5 months)

Clinical Professor for advanced 2nd degree RN students on psych rotation.

Capital Community College
Adjunct Clinical Professor
September 2006 - January 2007 (5 months)
clinical supervision of 1st year students on psych rotation

# NEW YORK CITY HEALTH & HOSPITAL CORPORATION

Assistant Director, Psychiatric Nursing Operations November 2004 - April 2006 (1 year 6 months)

Large public hospital serving the Borough of Queens in New York City.

Oversaw daily operations for a 24/7 clinical practice with budgetary responsibility for three acute adult inpatient psychiatric units and one

substance abuse detoxification unit. Managed 150 direct / indirect reports comprised of nurses, psychiatric technicians, and head nurses. Served as CNS for all other general hospital units. Investigated and presented all findings on incidents to senior leadership. Monitored infection control and quality assurance initiatives.

#### Selected Achievements

Planned and coordinated in-service training programs to prepare nursing and technical staff for Magnet survey and recognition as well as ensure conformance to regulatory standards and guidelines.

Eliminated on average 20 shifts of excessive staffing per month by realigning and balancing key resources to provide high-quality, low-cost services to specific patient populations across a 24/7 nursing practice.

Saved thousands of dollars by successfully recommending the elimination of staffing agencies representing hospital employees for OT consideration.

### Hartford Hospital/ The Institute of Living

**Unit Manager** 

May 2002 - November 2004 (2 years 7 months)

Managed 2 Acute inpatient psychiatric units.

Seriously persistantly mentally ill Unit and an acute dual diagnosis unit.

Responsibilities include the clinical and administrative oversight of these two units.

#### ST. FRANCIS CARE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH

Manager

December 2001 - May 2002 (6 months)

Residential healthcare organization for children and adolescents.

Served as a Nursing Manager for six special residential units serving 77 DCF custody children and adolescents as well as managed 35-bed dual diagnosis acute inpatient unit. Led 160 direct / indirect reports. Provided strategic direction and program planning in meeting organizational objectives. Upheld patient service-oriented / research-based culture across entire operation.

#### Selected Achievements

Reduced restraint and seclusion episodes monthly for six consecutive months by developing and implementing processes and procedures per hospital / regulatory guidelines.

Successfully trained Unit Managers in the effective scheduling and utilization of resources in support of meeting patient service requirements.

## BryLin Hospital

Assistant Director, Patient Care Services January 1999 - January 2001 (2 years 1 month)

Private inpatient psychiatric hospital.

Directed daily operations for a patient care services division with 90 direct / indirect reports. Held accountability for a 24/7 nursing operation, ensuring quality, cost-effective delivery of services for specific patient populations. Oversaw all Social Workers and Case Managers in both clinical and administrative areas.

#### NEW YORK STATE HEALTHCARE SYSTEM

Various titles leading up to Program Director January 1977 - January 1998 (21 years 1 month)

Multiple Locations over 21 years

# Education

University of Rochester

M.S, Psychiatric & Mental Health Nursing · (1994 - 1996)

State University of New York (SUNY) at Buffalo B.S, Nursing (1990 - 1992)

Genesee Community College Associate's Degree, Nursing (1975 - 1977)

Brebeuf Prep